i just think yeah maybe there are a lot
of people start
with the intention of
basically the criteria is
like yeah
i have a stressful life i want to get
into meditation because
um yeah i want to find
something which will bring you peace
pleasure yeah and um and the the minute
that there's this existential anxiety
that comes with the savage that i've
been running away from
whenever this um
then there's something wrong then i'm
not doing it right and then i need to
double down yeah yeah see and and like
as i said it often you know especially
when i when i'm criticizing techniques
and growing kind of a person on modern
time in itself it's not a problem if you know
in itself it's not a problem if you know
why you're doing it so if you genuinely
need to come down from a stressful life
yeah whatever do your yoga
relax stretch meditate watch your breath
but don't confuse that to be the dharma
because it's not
that's the thing
but many people would sort of
many people arrive at this
like i need to be free from stress but i
don't really want to you know
significantly impact or give up my life
that's fine but be clear about it but
what they arrive then is like oh yeah
find you you don't have to give it up
and you don't have to do any of this and
yes you are practicing see what these
sutures are teaching
and then they develop this view that
okay so nothing has to change for me and
i can be another hand
and because of that they will never
understand what real dharma is because again they
what real dharma is because again they
already conflated it and
by thinking that you know that it is
something that it isn't you will stop
trying to find out what it actually is
because you think you found it
so that's always the issue with all the
methods and techniques it's just
they never amount to practically
speaking to more than just a you know
calming realization distressing yourself
and so on but that's nowhere near
you know the peace that the buddha
teaches about the peace of it's like
peace be unable to suffer amid suffering
no matter whether you watch your
nostrils or not
whether you are being chopped
limb by limb by highway robbers or not
you're unable to suffer because your
mind's free from craving because you've
overcome it because your head is your
mind absolutely so strong yeah it's
unable to be affected by it and when the
buddha talks about meditation talks
about purifying mind from young
wholesome states
he does not talk about calming
timeless comes on account of being
unable to be disturbed
not on a kind of calm calm on top of the
disturbance or calm so that i can get this turned
or calm so that i can get this turned
you have to face the disturbance you
have to let it endure so then on account
of it become strong yes yeah and now a
person actually can remain clear about
their choice okay i started this thing
because i want to be free from stress
but actually
no i think i think i want to give
everything i'd be fully completely
beyond the possibility of suffering
and now i can actually and they would
commit to it rightly they would stop
doing their stress release techniques
and they actually would start taking the
teaching seriously without conflating
the two because people take the teaching
seriously by doing the stress relief techniques
by doing the stress relief techniques
and then they they just no longer able
to see the possibility yeah yeah because
yeah they think that and that's like the
bound to pick the issue there
so as long as things are not conflated
yeah make your own choices do what you
like but and then you realize the most you
but and then you realize the most you
can do is at least just
clarify the choice for people
you know whether they like it or not
doesn't matter at least
on some level they recognize that there
might be a choice
as opposed to yeah yeah this is it we
all teach the same just do that that
keeps the
authenticity the possibility of
authenticity alive exactly yeah at least
yeah i'm not doing it now but i know
it's on life support but at least it's
still plugged in
and like you you're saying the other day
like during the time of the buddha there were
during the time of the buddha there were
people who would disrobe and just out of
this uh understanding that like yeah i
can't do it so
by by admitting that it's on me yeah
they're still keeping this possibility
that exactly there is a more authentic
exactly there is a more authentic
available
rather than saying unless the dharma is
wrong and and then they they no longer
have that possibility available to them
yeah means that even people who failed
and disrobed who failed the teaching who
failed to fulfill it
still actually uh develop some wisdom
because they still see it still
they were still able to at least
understand what the practice was so
that's what they were saying no no
it was it was oscar was weak it wasn't
the teaching wasn't the teacher and they
would still respect it and still be
virtuous and still come keeping their
presets and so on
because they actually did develop the
clarity and they recognize okay no i
don't i don't i don't feel like going
that far and they accept the
responsibility for it they don't use it
as an excuse that's the difference
in other words like if things were you
know to go wrong in their life they
would still feel the weight of their
responsibility for not freeing
themselves from that life in its
entirety they wouldn't lie they would be unable
they wouldn't lie they would be unable
to lie to themselves about it so
the disrupt people of the buddha's time
were on average much wiser
than people today that are even
practicing the dharma
supposedly because again
because again
honesty is that prerequisite for the
dharma and if you're unable to be dishonest
and if you're unable to be dishonest
with yourself doesn't matter what threat
of pain will you know come as a result
of it
you're okay yet you are remaining on the
basis where the dharmas practice even if
you gave up that time and yeah there
were cases that were
put sixth time he destroyed
and then returned and then so because he
was authentic enough that although he
failed he reckoned and then go back and
sixth and after six times he became
another hand after sixth of the nation
eventually so he was doing the work
throughout these comings and goings
and obviously he was a bit more
impulsive but fundamentally he wasn't covering up
but fundamentally he wasn't covering up
his actions so when he disrobed he felt
the weight of it he felt the guilt of it
he felt the burden of it he felt the
pointlessness so and then it went back
so yeah it failed again but still never
covered it up which is why eventually he
succeeded by not covering it up you know
you just see okay i'm responsible for
this suffering yeah so so every time
that you're you're you're putting
yourself in that liability
you will just learn more and more to
find back because you know by enduring
the discomfort yeah because that's why
people would cover it up because it's
unpleasant yeah otherwise i don't know
if i said this
when i told you that story of like you
know meditating maureen but it was
similar when i sort of discovered the
suttas and started reading them more and
more it sort of
it sort of
it kind of clicked that okay if there's
anything to be right in this world as
far as his teachings in philosophy go
this seems like it
but then at the same time it was also
clear to me okay so i found what is
right that's it so that part of me was
satisfied so it's my choice now to either follow
so it's my choice now to either follow
it or just remain enjoying this
conviction that this is right
and but then immediately my mind itself
like considered okay so if i don't
follow this
whatever happens to me for the remaining
you know years of my life
whether it's
objectively my fault or not it's going
to be my fault internally subjectively
because i have not
i have not
well i've chosen clearly to not follow
the way out so i chosen to stay in the
environment where things can go one way
or the other way
and that environment is the environment
of samsara
and then i realized okay well that's not
the burden i can live with so whatever
then you realize
things things are objectively factually
out of your hands but now imagine you
feel responsible for things being out of
your hands
and so that's not a pleasant state to
live in
so you and that's exactly when when
willa says when a man discovers
suffering correctly there are only two
possible outcomes of that pain either
mental derangement or no no i gotta do
something about this noble search
so if you think you manage it you won't
you're gonna be overrun and and
basically buried under stress and
breakdowns and everything else
or you can actually do something about
it before all of that happens well at
least that's what became clear to me so
then it was it wasn't even an option
anymore so to speak for me too whether
to become a monk or not he was like just
when because
because
if anything's worth doing it's trying to
feel from the liability to suffering
which anything else you could possibly
do it's going to be within that yeah
and then again people are willing to
accept that deal for as long as they
don't recognize that it's still a matter
of their choice
like you know
i might be fine in this house because i
don't realize that the roof is on fire
and it's about to collapse
however if somehow i realize the roof is
on fire i can still choose to stay in
the house and enjoy the company and
everything else but if that roof come or
when death roof comes crashing i can't
blame anybody else i can't even blame
the one that started the fire
because i had all the options to apply
myself to find the escape
but i chosen not to and that's what
became clear to me that the roof is on
fire so yeah i don't have to do this but
if i don't do it i have absolutely no
excuse even if i again virtuous if i do
even if i again virtuous if i do
everything right for the rest of my life
sickness aging and death will have to
come to you to what's yours
to you to what's yours
things around you and that will all be
on me because i have not found a way out
of the crashing burning building
so
plain as a day
not a pleasant thing but at least it was
clear yeah
so like the four noble truths
i see as noble
or or
like the highest or the ultimate because
that is
because all intentions are contained
within this desire to to come out of
suffering so yeah so
so they are like
yeah you cannot have an intention
outside of
no no of that intention to come out of
suffering so
so what you're saying is basically
so you have no choice but to act out of
it so then how do you go about it how do
you act out of it yeah do you act like
by like that are you acting in a way
that results by to add adding more fuel
or are you acting the way that's
actually you know bringing you closer to
understand it and stop fueling it which
said in other ways
do i act out of craving or do i act to
understand the nature of craving these
are the two yeah
yeah yeah initially it's all rooted in
craving but craving can be abandoned by
the means of craving because because of
craving now you're not acting out as
much you're actually restraining
yourself you're enduring more all of
that does not fear craving as much
all of that brings it closer to
understanding because obviously the more you're able
because obviously the more you're able
to withstand it endure it that impulse
to act out out of greed or anger and so
on
well the the closer to it you become and
then it
you can see what needs to be seen
certain certain aspects of it certain
characteristics will become visible then
because they're not immediately covered up
they're not immediately covered up
usually through like just giving into
the desire or giving in to lashing out
and or giving into distraction and indolence
or giving into distraction and indolence
in oblivion because the craving is
allowed to enjoy you're you're able to
exactly get to know it a bit like yeah
yeah yeah endure familiarize you or
simply see by enduring it
you're actually
teaching yourself
to recognize that oh so it does not need
to be act upon immediately
because that even that is not not not
not apparent to people it's even that is
not seen as a choice yeah i don't know
what to do but at least i know that i
don't have to do anything
per se but i like yeah this is
unpleasant to endure but
that's one thing acting out will be then
seen oh but that's a separate thing i
used to think that's just one reaction
but the fact that i can endure it
the fact that i can endure it
means okay so there's a
possibility that it does not need to be
acted out
and then you come to see
that that implies this
and now that is very risky or that is
very dangerous yeah then the whole
parallel is between and then the
relationship will become even clearer of
course